Finding Aid for St. Columba Episcopal Church (Detroit, Mich.) records, 1917-2003
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
St. Columba Episcopal Church (Detroit, Mich.) records 1917-2003
St. Columba Episcopal Church (Detroit, Mich.)
04136 Ba 2 BA
St. Columba's Episcopal Church in Detroit, Michigan was established in 1913 as a mission extension of Old Christ Church, was incorporated, and continued functioning until 2003. The records group includes administrative records, vestry records, official church registers, and information on church activities.
5 linear feet
18 oversize volumes
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The record group (donor no. 1059 ) was transferred by the Episcopal Diocese of Michigan in 2004.
The record group is open to research.
St. Columba's Episcopal Church in Detroit, Michigan was established in 1913. Property abstracts show that the original church site was purchased in 1912 in a neighborhood subdivided for residences. The first church was a wood frame building on Manistique Avenue near Jefferson where Reverend Charles Ramsey assisted Rector William D. Maxom. Incorporated in 1917, the young church grew under the leadership of Rev. Otey R. Berkeley, rector from 1920 to 1957. In 1928, a new permanent church building was consecrated. During the Depression, the heavy weight of mortgage payments endangered the existence of the church. In 1938, the congregation organized a campaign, "Save the Church" to raise funds to restructure the debt on the building. In 1948, the members celebrated the final mortgage payment.
Rev. J. William Murchison served as rector from 1957 to 1962, succeeded by Rev. Robert J. Bickeley. Rev. Dexter Cheney, Rev. Gene Curry, and Rev. John Laycock served in succession. After flourishing in the 1950s, St. Columba experienced decline in membership, but continued to serve the neighborhood. St. Columba Outreach ministry was incorporated in 1984 and was active in such programs as Headstart, a thrift shop, and job placement service. Despite these efforts, St. Columba was closed by the Diocese of Detroit in 2003.
For more historical detail, researchers may want to consult Through the Years, 1834-1988, A History of the Episcopal Diocese of Michigan, published by the Chapter of the Cathedral Church of St. Paul, 1989.
The record group is divided into four series: Administration, Vestry Records, Church Registers, and Activities.
Subjects:
St. Columba Episcopal Church (Detroit, Mich.); Church records and registers--Michigan--Detroit.; Detroit (Mich.)--Church history.; Episcopal Church--Michigan--Detroit.; Marriage records--Michigan--Detroit.; Registers of births, etc.--Michigan--Detroit.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
St. Columba Episcopal Church (Detroit, Mich.); Churches--Michigan--Detroit.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Administration
  The Administration series includes two subseries. Corporate Papers contains the articles of incorporation in 1917, by laws for St. Columba Community Outreach in 1984, and the Michigan Annual Reports for both entities. The 1912 abstracts for the original property purchase for two lots are included. Finance subseries includes the accountings for Save the Church Fund in the 1930s and 1940s and more recent reviewed financial statements from the 1990s.
  - Corporate Papers
    - Property Abstracts 1912, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Articles of Incorporation, St. Columba Church 1917 (Box 1)
    - Articles of Incorporation, St. Columba Church Community Outreach 1984 (Box 1)
    - Michigan Annual Reports 1935, 1938-1996, 3 folders (Box 1)
      (with some gaps)
  - Financial Accounts
    - Parish Budget 1923 (Box 1)
    - Building Fund Campaigns 1926, 1929 (Box 1)
    - Vestry Sheets, collections 1930-1941, 10 folders (Box 1)
    - Save the Church (STC) Campaign
      - Campaign materials, 3 folders (Box 1)
      - STC Fund
        - Pledges 1937 (Box 1)
        - 1936-1939, 3 folders (Box 1)
        - 1939-1940 (Volume 1)
        - 1940-1941 (Volume 2)
        - 1941-1943 (Volume 3)
        - 1943 (Volume 4)
        - 1944 (Volume 5)
        - 1945 (Volume 6)
        - 1946 (Volume 7)
        - 1947 (Volume 8)
        - 1948 (Volume 9)
    - General and Berkeley Memorial Funds 1962-1968 (Box 1)
    - Audit 1993-1994 (Box 1)
    - Reviewed Financial Statements 1997-2003, 2 folders (Box 1)
- Vestry Records
  Vestry Records include subseries for envelope collections, early correspondence, Vestry meeting minutes and Annual Meeting Reports which form the bulk of this record group. The Vestry met monthly to manage the business of the church. They compiled an annual report each year that was presented to the entire congregation.
  - Envelope records
    - 1915-1917 (Volume 10)
    - Undated (Volume 11)
    - Undated (Volume 12)
    - Undated (Volume 13)
  - Vestry correspondence 1921-1938 (Box 1)
  - Vestry Minutes
    - 1917-1924 (Box 1)
      (bound journal)
    - 1940-1945, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - 1959-1969, 9 folders (Box 1)
    - 1970-1997, 28 folders (Box 2)
    - 1998-2003, 6 folders (Box 3)
  - Annual Reports
    - 1935 (Box 3)
    - 1939 (Box 3)
    - 1940-1943 (Box 3)
      (bound volume)
    - 1941-1943 (Box 3)
    - 1944-1985, 42 folders (Box 3)
    - 1988-2002, 15 folders (Box 3)
  - Parochial Reports 1973-2003, 6 folders (Box 4)
- Church Registers
  Church Registers include bound registers of records of baptisms, confirmations, marriages, burials, and transfers in and out of the parish. Parish Reports to the Episcopal Church contain yearly compilations of statistics on activities and financial data.
  - Baptism
    - 1941-1975 (Volume 14)
    - 1975-2003 (Box 4)
  - Confirmation 1941-2002 (Volume 15)
  - Marriage
    - 1930-1940 (Box 4)
    - 1940-1947 (Box 4)
    - 1947-2003 (Volume 16)
  - Burial 1948-2003 (Volume 17)
  - Mixed
    - 1916-1930 (Volume 18)
    - 1917-1920 (Box 4)
    - 1928-1940 (Box 4)
  - Transfers
    - Out
      - 1964-1970 (Box 4)
      - 1972-1987, 3 folders (Box 4)
      - 1990-1999 (Box 4)
      - 2002-2004 (Box 4)
    - In 1941-2001, 3 folders (Box 4)
- Activities
  Activities series includes subseries on the history of the church including photographs of World War II veterans, a St. Columba's Country Fair, 1965, and several church interior shots. Researchers may want to look at Publications and member directories for historical data. The Berkeley Memorial Lectures were held in 1960, 1962, and 1963. Covenant Worship Committee in the 1980s reflects the ecumenical movement arising from Vatican II in the Roman Catholic Church.
  - Photographs
    - World War II Veterans (Box 5)
    - Country Fair 1965 (Box 5)
    - Church interior (Box 5)
  - Parish history
    - Anniversaries, 35th, 50th, 75th, 85th (Box 5)
    - Closing 2003 (Box 5)
    - Directories 1944-1996, 3 folders (Box 5)
    - Memorial windows, kneeling bench covers (Box 5)
    - Publications (Box 5)
  - Berkeley Memorial Lectures 1958-1963, 3 folders (Box 5)
  - Covenant Worship Committee 1978, 1982 (Box 5)
  - Flower and Candle Memorial Fund 1990-1996 (Box 5)
  - Women's Club
    - Women's Club minutes
      - 1914-1919 (Box 5)
      - 1919-1927 (Box 5)
    - Women's Auxiliary attendance 1922-1927 (Box 5)
    - Women's Club account book 1925-1932 (Box 5)